<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-01-17T09:14:08-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ali Siddiqui</title><subtitle>Oceanographer</subtitle><author><name>Ali Siddiqui</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Road to Collective Bargaining for TRU-UE</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-road-to-collective-bargaining-for-tru-ue" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Road to Collective Bargaining for TRU-UE" /><published>2023-06-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-06-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/uenews</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-road-to-collective-bargaining-for-tru-ue"><![CDATA[<p>This <a href="https://www.ueunion.org/ue-news/2023/the-road-to-collective-bargaining-for-tru-ue">article</a> was originally published in UE news on June 3, 2023.</p>

<p class="centered"><img src="../figures/image-johns-hopkins-organizing.jpg" width="1000" pxl="" /></p>
<p class="centered">TRU-UE launches their card campaign with a rally on October 25, 2022.</p>

<p><strong>By Ali Siddiqui, Kristin Brig-Ortiz, and Andrew S Eneim, TRU-UE</strong></p>

<p>Graduate workers at Johns Hopkins University began collective bargaining as Teachers and Researchers United-United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (TRU-UE) with the university administration on May 10, 2023. Earlier this spring, graduate students at Hopkins won a historic vote for the formation of TRU-UE with a 97 percent majority, with 2,053 graduate students voting yes and 67 voting no. TRU-UE now represents around 3,200 PhD workers across the Johns Hopkins Homewood, East Baltimore and Washington DC campuses.</p>

<p>The Bargaining Committee’s current proposals are a result of years of grassroots organizing over important issues that have plagued the graduate student community at JHU. We are demanding a guaranteed, on-time, respectable living wage; meaningful and effective grievance procedures; safe and reliable transport and workspace facilities; worker protection for international students; and a long-term, serious commitment to the city of Baltimore, in which the university is based.</p>

<p>The unionization movement started in 2014, when the university administration began implementing the new strategic plan for the next decade.This new plan included reducing the number of graduate students on campus and hiring more adjunct faculty for teaching. In an academic culture where graduate students are already at the bottom of the feeding chain, this was a breaking point. A group of PhD students responded by initiating the TRU campaign and started organizing around the issue of increasing graduate student voices in decision making on campus. Then, in 2016, the National Labor Relations Board (NLRB) voted 3-1 that graduate students serving as teaching assistants and research assistants were university employees with a right to collectively bargain. At this point, TRU moved towards a union election to formalize its collective bargaining rights on campus.</p>

<p>It took longer than planned for TRU to elect a union, thanks in part to changes under the Trump administration, the COVID-19 pandemic, and the university’s continued insistence that grad students are not employees. Even so, TRU’s advocacy in different areas of grad student and campus life led to meaningful wins, particularly securing a <a href="https://www.jhunewsletter.com/article/2017/09/editorial-we-must-continue-the-fight-for-graduate-student-healthcare">dental and vision health insurance coverage package for all Arts &amp; Sciences grad students</a>, <a href="https://www.jhunewsletter.com/article/2017/09/university-grants-grad-students-parental-leave">paid parental leave</a>, and <a href="https://www.jhunewsletter.com/article/2021/06/hopkins-will-provide-additional-covid-19-relief-funds-to-students">COVID emergency relief funds</a> across all campuses. The fact that such benefits were not already in place at a prestigious university like JHU says everything about the state of graduate student affairs in our universities.</p>

<p>TRU organizers have also protested alongside other campus activist organizations. Starting in 2018, TRU joined Students Against Private Police (SAPP) and Refuel Our Future to organize against contracts that Hopkins had with the US Department of Immigrations Customs and Enforcement (ICE), forcing JHU <a href="https://www.jhunewsletter.com/article/2019/09/university-will-not-renew-its-contracts-with-ice">to drop its contracts with ICE in September 2019</a>. The following year, TRU members were involved with the <a href="https://www.jhunewsletter.com/article/2019/05/university-leadership-condemns-escalation-of-garland-sit-in">Garland Hall Sit-In in May 2019</a> to protest the proposed JHU private police force. Since then, the union has stood in solidarity with a number of labor unions and other local organizations in the Baltimore community as they fight for the rights they deserve. They always have our backs, so we need to have theirs!</p>

<p>In September of 2021, the TRU Organizing Committee unanimously voted to affiliate with UE and began preparing for a card campaign to finally win legal recognition. This choice was an easy one, as we quickly realized that our values of rank-and-file democracy and social justice are aligned with UE. This was the beginning of a relationship that would quickly grow into an organized, mobilized, and dedicated bargaining unit that was ready to take the respect and dignity we deserve. Grad workers across JHU were sick and tired of the mistreatment we faced as we were forced to work through COVID in substandard facilities without access to reliable testing and PPE, and throughout the following year we grew through our deep dedication to the rank-and-file driven campaign.</p>

<p>2022 was a pivotal year for the campaign, as TRU had more organizers than ever before. Once there was a steady organizing committee of more than 150 graduate students, we publicly launched our card campaign in late October, with a huge rally. By mid-November, over 2,000 grad students had signed their cards. As expected, Hopkins rejected our request for voluntary recognition, and we then submitted our cards to the NLRB, while planning for our union election at the beginning of the spring semester. During January 30-31, 2023, over 60 percent of all graduate students at JHU went to the polls. As the votes were being counted in the local NLRB office in downtown Baltimore, the sound of “yes” echoed around the room hundreds of times over; over 97% of votes were union YES. Before the official count was even announced, we knew we had made it.</p>

<p>After hearing from other unions’ experiences, we organized a bargaining committee election. We broke the university into five divisions, and each division voted for four to five bargaining committee representatives. We elected 22 members who would represent TRU-UE at the bargaining table. The bargaining committee prepared for negotiations over the next month until their first bargaining session on May 10, 2023. To show support for the elected bargainers, TRU held a huge rally in Wyman quad in front of Shriver Hall, the building in which the first bargaining session took place. Through the rally, the union definitely caught the attention of the university administration, who have since complained about how the rally-goers “damaged new sod.”</p>

<p>When we think back on our wins, particularly this year, we have witnessed an incredible amount of dedicated and targeted organizing in departments and labs across campus that has led to increased awareness of and involvement in the campaign. Since we began organizing with UE last year, we have seen our organizing core grow to over 160 active organizers covering nine university divisions. This number is still growing. Through our organizing, we have especially focused on spaces where our reach was limited to communicate about the unionization effort as far and wide as possible. To do so, we had to create building leads and divisional coordinators who worked with department organizers to perform lab and office walkthroughs, coordinate one-on-one conversations, and ensure each and every graduate student was reached. Our victories are thus a testament to the hard work of all the department organizers who were relentless in their outreach and who made sure that by the day of the union election vote, every graduate student on campus had signed up to come to the polls.</p>

<p><em>TRU members were assisted by Field Organizers <strong>Lyndsey O’Day</strong> and <strong>Valentina Luketa</strong> and Project Staff <strong>Royce Brown</strong>, <strong>Andrew Eneim</strong>, <strong>Townsend Nelson</strong> and <strong>Peter Weck</strong>.</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Ali Siddiqui</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="unions," /><category term="TRU" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article was originally published in UE news on June 3, 2023.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Our union is our power and today we take it</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/our-union-is-our-power-and-today-we-take-it" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Our union is our power and today we take it" /><published>2023-01-31T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-31T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/union-JHU-newsletter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/our-union-is-our-power-and-today-we-take-it"><![CDATA[<p>This <a href="https://www.jhunewsletter.com/article/2023/01/our-union-is-our-power-and-today-we-take-it">article</a> was originally published in the Johns Hopkins University student newsletter on January 31 2023.</p>

<p>After years of struggling with the University and barely improving working conditions, almost 3,200 doctoral students at Hopkins are finally voting to form a graduate student worker union. This is the culmination of years of organizing for a living wage, protections for international students, fair grievance procedures and so much more that graduate workers need to lead a dignified life.</p>

<p>These concerns have continued to go unaddressed, and graduate workers are now saying that enough is enough. Unionization is our opportunity to be treated as equals by negotiating a contract that guarantees research and teaching conditions that will allow graduate student workers, and in turn, this University, to thrive.</p>

<p>Why would we go through the trouble of forming a union? The answer is simple. We do not feel valued.</p>

<p>Over the years, Hopkins administration has failed to prioritize its doctoral students. After almost a decade, the minimum Krieger School of Arts and Sciences stipends were <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1IiRh4s6HiNUssYVsTWOOEyi3xEgizqiJ/view">raised to $34,500 this fall</a>. Despite the raise, these stipends remain below the <a href="https://livingwage.mit.edu/counties/24510">cost of living in Baltimore</a>, affecting how graduate students can do their research and teaching.</p>

<p>In fact, most schools do not even have a system of raising salaries each year to account for inflation. We have colleagues in the world-renowned Bloomberg School of Public Health being given stipends as low as <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1N4vKYJ85nsyofnz5MHBhFgP3Egkbchyy/view?usp=sharing">$26,000 per year</a>.</p>

<p>With such pride in being the first research university in the U.S. and topping the U.S. <a href="https://hub.jhu.edu/2023/01/09/nsf-higher-education-research-spending-2021/">rankings in research spending</a> for 43 years, one would expect the University to set an example and spend its money on paying the people who actually run the labs and produce the research output that it is so proud of.</p>

<p>However, up until 2018, its graduate students did not have vision and dental health insurance as part of their support package. Furthermore, every year Hopkins <a href="https://www.baltimoresun.com/education/bs-md-hopkins-graduate-rally-20221025-mwzcat3a35b2ndlphivztmuyte-story.html">fails to pay</a> its graduate students on time, despite several attempts to demonstrate late pay issues through testimonials from more than 100 students across the School of Medicine, School of Public Health and Whiting School of Engineering over the last few years.</p>

<p>It is simply a tragedy that graduate workers have been treated so unfairly at Hopkins while the University rakes in hundreds of millions of dollars in <a href="https://www.jhunewsletter.com/article/2021/11/university-discusses-endowment-budget-surplus-at-town-hall">surplus</a> annually.</p>

<p>Founded in 2014, Teachers and Researchers United (TRU) has made significant gains in addressing graduate worker needs, including campaigning for better health insurance and childcare packages for its graduate students. TRU also supported such movements as <a href="https://www.jhunewsletter.com/article/2019/02/jhtoo-seeks-to-revoke-accused-professors-tenure">JHToo</a>, which was formed to support survivors of sexual assault and hold the University accountable for mishandled cases.</p>

<p>Similar movements of graduate worker unionization have swept the country over the last few years. As this <a href="https://www.chronicle.com/article/graduate-students-win-pay-raises-as-union-efforts-surge">wave of higher education organizing</a> has grown, doctoral students at <a href="https://news.yale.edu/2023/01/09/yale-graduate-students-vote-form-labor-union">Yale University</a>, <a href="http://nugradworkers.org/">Northwestern University</a>, <a href="http://bugradworkers.org/">Boston University</a> and <a href="http://mitgsu.org/">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</a> among others, have recently won union elections and their bargaining units have started (or will soon start) negotiations with their universities.</p>

<p>Since the University’s undergraduate program is consistently ranked in the <a href="https://hub.jhu.edu/2022/09/12/us-news-college-rankings-2022/">top 10</a> in the U.S. and competes with the likes of the above universities, it’s about time it treats its doctoral students with the respect that we deserve, too.</p>

<p>What lies ahead?</p>

<p>The administration has failed to live up to the standards of which it so eloquently boasts. It has shown us that demands from graduate students on campus will go unheard unless we stand up for our rights.</p>

<p>Today, we vote. We let Hopkins know what its graduate students think about their working conditions.</p>

<p>Ultimately, our unionization effort is one of hope — hope that our academic spaces will nurture healthy and safe working conditions, that every doctoral student can carry out excellent research without worrying about their bank statements and that we are treated with the respect that we deserve.</p>

<p>We are manifesting a future in which Hopkins treats its workers with respect and invests in what truly allows it to run: its graduate student workers. Join us by voting TRU-UE YES on Jan. 31.</p>

<p><em>Ali Siddiqui is a fifth-year doctoral candidate in the Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences.</em></p>

<p><em>Kristin Brig-Ortiz is a sixth-year doctoral candidate in the Department of the History of Medicine</em></p>]]></content><author><name>Ali Siddiqui</name></author><category term="blog" /><category term="unions" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article was originally published in the Johns Hopkins University student newsletter on January 31 2023.]]></summary></entry></feed>